Guide to the Phi Kappa Psi, North Carolina Alpha Chapter (Duke University) Records, 1934-1978
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Phi Kappa Psi, North Carolina Alpha Chapter (Duke University) records 1934-1978
University Archives, Duke University
Phi Kappa Psi. North Carolina Alpha Chapter (Duke University).
1.0 Linear Feet about 1,000 Items
The North Carolina Alpha Chapter of Phi Kappa Psi began in 1934 and was the fifty-third Phi Kappa Psi chapter in the nation.
The types of material include bound volumes, clippings, rosters, photographs, and miscellaneous notes. Major topics include student life at Duke University, rushing, pledging, hazing, community service, alcohol policies, Interfraternity Council relations, accounting, social activities, chapter establishment, and governance. The material ranges in date from 1934-1978.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Phi Kappa Psi, North Carolina Alpha Chapter (Duke University) Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1976-1983.
Historical Note
The North Carolina Alpha Chapter of Phi Kappa Psi began in 1934 and was the fifty-third Phi Kappa Psi chapter in the nation.
During the late 1960s, the Chapter was disbanded due to students serving in Vietnam. The fraternity had 66 members in spring 1968 but had dropped to six members by fall 1969. The numbers eventually rose; there were 22 members in spring 1970.
The Chapter participated in Greek Week, various social outings with Little Sisters, and general philanthropy projects. One famous prank pulled by the fraternity involved members decorating a dormitory tower clock in Mickey Mouse attire (1979). The chapter was well-known for its annual James Valvano Memorial Celebrity Auction, which benefited the children's cancer research program at Duke Children's Hospital. In 2001, Phi Kappa Psi's housing privileges were revoked. The fraternity has not been chartered at Duke University since that time.
Collection Overview
The types of material include bound volumes, clippings, rosters, photographs, and miscellaneous notes. Major topics include student life at Duke University, rushing, pledging, hazing, community service, alcohol policies, Interfraternity Council relations, accounting, social activities, chapter establishment, and governance. The material ranges in date from 1934-1978.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Phi Kappa Psi. North Carolina Alpha Chapter (Duke University).
Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions
Duke University -- Societies, etc
College Students -- Alcohol Use -- North Carolina -- Durham
Greek letter societies -- North Carolina -- Durham
Hazing
Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.)
Related Material
Photograph Collection
Duke University Archives
Fraternities and Sororities Collection
Duke University Archives
Interfraternity Council Records
Duke University Archives
Panhellenic Council Records
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Celebrity Auctions, 1976-1985 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and miscellaneous notes, 1934, 1979, 1986
  - Committees, reports and minutes, 1958-1959
  - Directory of members, 1935-1985
  - Fraternity family tree, 1969-1983
  - Photographs, 1968-1970, 1987, undated
  - Minutes, November 12, 1934-April 17, 1941
  - Minutes, January 16, 1950-February 4, 1959
  - Minutes, February 22, 1959-November 12, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, December 8, 1969-December 8, 1974
  - Minutes, December 15, 1974-September 17, 1978
  - Sorority Board Composite Photographs, 1956, 1958-1960, 1963-1974 (Opaperfolder 1)